A Guide to the Joy S. Starr Collection on Vale History, 1964-1995
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Joy S. Starr Collection on Vale History, 1964-1995
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-18
1.3 linear feet
The Joy S. Starr Collection on Vale History spanning the years 1964-1995 consists of 1.3 linear feet and contains correspondence, notes, maps, photocopies, newspaper clippings, an unpublished manuscript, articles, notebooks, oral history tape cassettes, photographs, and negatives.
Starr, Joy S. (1931 - )
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Joy S. Starr in 1996.
Historical and Biographical Information
Joy Eloise Smith was born on May 1, 1931 to Capt. George Leonard Smith, U.S.N. and Bradie Baker in Winnebago County, Illinois. Her father, inventor of the Smith-Asbury mechanism, was a descendent of some of the earliest New England and Virginia families. Joy graduated from the Holton-Arms School in Bethesda, Maryland in 1949 and later graduated from Wheaton College in Norton, Massachusetts. She married Nicholas Starr of Alexandria, Virginia in August 1963. At the time of her marriage she was the State chairman of the District Daughters of the American Revolution Junior Membership Committee.
In 1964, the couple bought Appledore, (also known as Poplar Vale) an historic house constructed around 1806 located at 3000C Fox Mill Road in Oakton, VA. An amateur historian, Joy undertook extensive research on the surrounding neighborhoods of Vale, Navy, Pender, and Floris. She contributed to Edward Wagstaff’s Fairfax City Times column “Historically Speaking” writing articles about Appledore, Vale, and Fox Mill’s history in 1964 and 1965.
In January 1968, the Starrs helped establish the Navy-Vale Community League which fought for the community’s interests. In 1990, she served as Chairman of the Fox Mill Communities Preservation Association History Committee. The following year, Joy completed an unpublished manuscript entitled “Vale History: From Money’s Corner through Difficult” which explored the history of the Vale and Fox Mill neighborhoods including 18th and 19th century houses. The Starrs sold Appledore in 2000 to developers who built new houses on the property while preserving the historic house.
Scope and Content
The Joy S. Starr Collection on Vale History spanning the years 1964-1995 consists of 1.3 linear feet and contains correspondence, notes, maps, photocopies, newspaper clippings, an unpublished manuscript, articles, notebooks, oral history tape cassettes, photographs, and negatives. Subjects include the history of the Vale and Fox Mill area of Oakton, Virginia.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Appledore (Fairfax County, Va.); Historic buildings - Virginia - Fairfax County; Oakton (Va.) - History; Starr, Joy S. (1931 - ); Sutphin, Vincent D. (1917-2014); Vale, (Va.) - History
Container List
- Fox Mill Community Preservation Association, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Navy-Vale Community League, Minutes & Correspondence, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- “Vale History: From Moneys Corner Through Difficult”, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Research Notes, Vale History General Notes, 1965-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research Notes, “Appledore” History, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Research Notes, Bennett Family Genealogy, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Research Notes, Deeds, Tax Records, & Cemeteries, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Research Notes, Houses (existing), Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Research Notes, House research by Susan Leigh, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Research Notes, Maps and Illustrations, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Newspaper clippings, 1964-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Oral History tapes (with Mrs. Gallery and Vincent D. Sutphin 5/8/1990) [2 cassettes and 1 floppy disk, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Research Notes, Public Buildings - Second Fox Mill Site, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Research Notes, Roads, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Research Notes, Vale Community Center, 1964-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Research Notes, Sources, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photo binder, Fox Mill Communities Preservation Association History Committee [35 photos of historic sites in Fox Mill], 1990 July (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photo, General Pershing’s two horses Kidron and Jeff, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photos and contact sheet, Vale School, Vale Church and cemetery, 1941 [11 photographs], Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photos, Greenstone ax found near bridge on Stuart Mill Road [4 photographs], Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photos, Vale School [2 photographs], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photos and negatives, Fox Mill site stonework [16 photographs], 1976-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Photos and negatives, Unusual tree at Appledore/Poplar Vale, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Contact sheet and negative, Vale United Methodist Church, House at 11900 Bennett Road, Unidentified House, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Contact sheet and negative, Vale United Methodist Church Cemetery, House at 11321 Waples Mill Road, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Contact sheet and negative, Appledore/Poplar Vale, House at 3010 Fox Mill Road, House at 3017 Fox Mill Road, Unidentified house, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Contact sheet and negative, Appledore/Poplar Vale, Vale Schoolhouse, House at 11900 Bennett Road, House at 3017 Fox Mill Road, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)